<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The entrie to Christianitie, or, An admonition to householders very necessary for instruction of their families, as also others, whereby, with some some small labour, they may attaine to the vnderstanding of the Christian faith: (if holy, and Christian exercises, as prayers, and such sanctified meanes) be devoutly vsed. Drawne out of the sacred Scriptures, as also prooued by the iudgement of famous learned writers. Very fit for this diseased and sickly age, where-in popish ignorance and deuilish atheisme dooth so abound. By Thomas Wats, minister of the word of God.</title>
            <title>Entrie to Christianitie.</title>
            <author>Watts, Thomas, fl. 1571-1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25128</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106295</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842013</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842013</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6636</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14831)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6636)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 719:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The entrie to Christianitie, or, An admonition to householders very necessary for instruction of their families, as also others, whereby, with some some small labour, they may attaine to the vnderstanding of the Christian faith: (if holy, and Christian exercises, as prayers, and such sanctified meanes) be devoutly vsed. Drawne out of the sacred Scriptures, as also prooued by the iudgement of famous learned writers. Very fit for this diseased and sickly age, where-in popish ignorance and deuilish atheisme dooth so abound. By Thomas Wats, minister of the word of God.</title>
                  <title>Entrie to Christianitie.</title>
                  <author>Watts, Thomas, fl. 1571-1589.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T. O[rwin] for Thomas Woodcocke, dwelling at the signe of the blacke Beare,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (A1 blank) B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious education of children --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6636:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6636:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Entrie to Chriſtianitie, or, <hi>An admonition to Houſholders, very</hi> neceſſary for inſtruction of their Families, <hi>as alſo others, whereby, with ſome ſmall labour,</hi> they may attaine to the vnderſtanding <hi>of the Chriſtian faith: (if holy, and Chriſtian</hi> exerciſes, as prayers, and ſuch ſanctified meanes) be devoutly vſed.</p>
            <p>Drawne out of the ſacred Scriptures, as <hi>alſo prooued by the iudgement of famous</hi> learned writers.</p>
            <p>Very fit for this diſeaſed and ſickly age, <hi>where-in popish ignorance and deuilish</hi> Atheiſme dooth ſo abound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Thomas Wats, Miniſter of the</hi> word of God.</p>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>T. O.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Woodcocke,</hi> dwelling at the Signe of <hi>the blacke Beare. 1589.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="religious_treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:6636:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6636:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE ENTRIE <hi>to Christianitie.</hi> That it behoueth Parents to bring vp their <hi>Children in the knowledge of</hi> Gods Word.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Authoritie of the Scriptures.</hi> Gen. 18, 19. Exod. 12.26, 27, 13, 8, 14. Deut 4, 9, 10.6, 6, 7, 20. <hi>to the ende,</hi> 11, 18.19, 32, 46. Ioſh. 4, 21, 22, 23, 24. 1. King. 2, 1, 3. Pſalm. 78, 3, 4, 5.6. Eſd. 38, 29. Eph. 6, 4. 2. Tim. 1, 5. 2. Ioh. 4. <hi>Iudgement of the Learned.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>O you not coumpt thoſe fathers to haue diſcharged their whole du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which do teach their children to ſaye the tenne Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Lords Prayer; and the Articles of the faith: and ſay they haue done what they can?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſwer.</label> It is moſt ſure they haue to render accoumpt vnto God for a far greater matter then the teaching them to ſpeake theſe things, for they are to ſee that they vnderſtand them, they are to inſtruct them in all poynts of true Religion; they are to ſhew them the ſteps of godlineſſe: they are to exhort them with al diligence, yea and to charge them to feare God, and to walke in his waies.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> All men are not able to doo this you ſpeake of.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6636:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <label>Aunſwer.</label> The more ſhame for them, that they will be fathers, before they can do that which is the duety of fathers, and the more heauie iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment tarieth for them, for caſting away, and ſpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the ſoules of their children. <hi>Maiſter Gyff. Catechiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We all be carefull and very circumſpect in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding for the cattell that are bred at our houſe, and we are much buſied and take great paines about them, and the like diligence we vſe alſo in looking vnto young trees, and plants; but our children are much more of valewe then all cattell, and they are the tender plants of the <hi>Paradiſe of God:</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not therefore with words be ſpoken, how greatly the wicked and cruell negligence of thoſe parents is to be deteſted, which ſo much neglect, and ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſet by theſe moſt worthie creatures on the earth, and theſe goodlie plants of the Church and heauenly <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> that they are mooued with no care of their good education. Let Parents therfore meditate this ſaying, <hi>Math. 18, 10. See that ye deſpiſe not one of theſe little ones: for I ſay vnto you, that in heauen their Angels alwaies behold the face of my father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> But a great ſort thinke them-ſelues well excuſed, if they can pretend either their owne igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or other buſineſſes. But ſuch excuſe is rather to be lamented then admitted. If Parents be ſo ignorant, that they can neither teach their children
<pb facs="tcp:6636:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſincere doctrine of the Catechiſme, nor yet be able to diſcerne between vertues and vices, things that bee honeſt and vnhoneſt, ſeemely and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely: ſurely ſuch excuſe is a moſt grieuous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation of them-ſelues. And touching buſineſſes, the thing that is pretended is not only fooliſh, ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, and odious: but alſo vngodlie, wicked, and blaſphemous. For, as in all the ſubſtance of the houſe, no treaſure is more worthie then be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſo among all buſineſſes, this ought to bee the chiefeſt, that the children bee rightly cared for: and well looked vnto. <hi>Paul. <hi>Eitz. Ethic. Doctr. lib. 3. cap. 4.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, a word or two of the bringing vp of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and preparing them to confirmation. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I would God the ould order were duely obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that they were inſtructed perfectly to knowe Religion, and their duetie to God, and might bee brought before the congregation, and make an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen profeſſion of their faith, with promiſe, that neither tribulation, nor anguiſh, nor perſecution, nor famine, nor nakedneſſe, nor fire, nor ſword, nor life, nor death: ſhall euer make them deny their faith. Hereof might much be ſpoken, but I will be ſhort. The whole ſtandeth in knowledge and in the feare of God, that they may know God, and walke before him in reuerence and in feare: and ſerue him in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the daies of their life. The <hi>Iewes</hi> are a miſerable peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:6636:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> they liue in error, they die in their owne bloud; yet haue they ſo much vnderſtanding, that they bring vp their children in the knowledge of God: and that knowledge they teach out of the word of God. They remember what charge God gaue them: <hi>Thou ſhalt teach them thy ſonnes, and thy ſonnes ſonnes, &amp;c.</hi> Let vs looke vpon our children, as vpon the great bleſſings of God. They are the Lords veſſells ordained to honour, let vs keepe them cleane: they are <hi>Chriſts lambes,</hi> and <hi>ſheepe of his flocke,</hi> let vs leade them foorth into wholeſome <hi>Paſture.</hi> They are the ſeed-plot of heauen, let vs water them that God may giue the increaſe; <hi>their Angels behold the face of God,</hi> let vs <hi>not offend them,</hi> they are the <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> and <hi>tabernacles of the holie Ghoſt:</hi> Let vs not ſuffer the foule ſpirit to poſſeſſe them, and dwell in them. God ſaith, <hi>Your children are my children. They are the ſonnes of God.</hi> They are <hi>borne a new,</hi> and are well ſhapen in beautifull proportion: make them not monſters. Hee is a monſter whoſoeuer knoweth not God. By you they are borne into the world, be carefull alſo that by your meanes, they may be begotten vnto God, you are carefull to traine them in mixture &amp; comly behauiour of the bodie, ſeeke alſo to faſhion their minds vnto Godlineſſe; you haue brought them to the fountaine of Baptiſme to receiue the marke of Chriſt, bring them vp in knowledge, and watch
<pb facs="tcp:6636:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> ouer them that they be not loſt. <hi>That ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God Biſhop Iewel in a treatiſe of the Sacraments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euery houſholder is here appoynted a Biſhop of his houſe. And a little after, Houſholders therfore muſt be carefull, that they haue the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of matters diuine: otherwiſe how ſhall they inſtruct them that are of their houſhold? <hi>Paule</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth not <hi>women to teach in the Church, but commaundeth them to learne of their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands at home:</hi> what huſband ſhall teach his wife, himſelfe being vnlearned and ignorant? in the ſixt of <hi>Deutronomie</hi> it is well ſet downe Therefore firſt, <hi>And theſe words which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund thee, ſhall be in thine heart.</hi> And then immediatly after it is added: <hi>And thou ſhalt teach them to thy ſonnes.</hi> And this thing is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graft almoſt in all men, and ſpecially in the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, to hold faſt and highlye eſteeme the things that they haue learned of their Parents. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it mattereth much what is taught by Parents to their poſteritie. Now-adaies wee heare this thing common: I will beleeue that which my fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers beleeued. Thou beleeueſt well, if ſo be that they beleeued well: and if they haue deliuered to the poſterities ſuch things as be good. Otherwiſe the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Turkes</hi> vnder this pretence defend their errors, which they haue receiued of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Let euery houſholder therefore beware and take good héed what he teach his houſhold. A man
<pb facs="tcp:6636:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> may finde houſholders which be ſo ignorant and vnſkilfull in things diuine, that they can by no meanes performe that thing which is heere com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. Let ſuch not be aſhamed to heare and learne, yea, if it were of little boyes, the things which hitherto they haue not knowne. A man may finde alſo ſome houſholders which will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their duetie in teaching Religion, although they bee able to do it. Againe, a man may finde others, which by wicked force doo euen let their houſholds from learning the things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Religion and ſeruice of God. But herein it belongeth to the Magiſtrate to vſe his office, to erect and ſet forward publike ſchooles. <hi>Wolf. Muſc. in Pſal. 78. verſ. 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Speake men of diſcipline neuer ſo much, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine they of the want of Church-gouernment neuer ſo lowde, preach they, teach they neuer ſo much abroade, vnleſſe they will begin diſcipline in reforming their houſes, and giue Religion ſome roume at home, they ſhal trauaile much, and profit little. Let there be neuer ſo good lawes in Cities, neuer ſo pure orders in Churches; if there be no practiſe at home: if fathers of families vſe not doctrine, and diſcipline in their houſes, and ioyne their hands to Magiſtrate and Miniſters: they may indéed, but vniuſtly, as many haue done, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine that their Children are corrupted abroade, when they were before, and are ſtill corrupted at
<pb facs="tcp:6636:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> home. <hi>Exhortation for houſhold Diſcipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both maried men, and Monkes, and wiues, commonlye haue this contention among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, who may learne moſt ſcriptures. <hi>Hierom. in Pſal. 33. Fathers, bring vp your children in the learning, and nurture of the Lord, and teach them the holie Scriptures. <hi>Ignatius Epiſt. 6.</hi>
               </hi> If ye be willing that the holie Scriptures may become ſweete vnto you, and that Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements may profite you as they ought, withdrawe your ſelues from worldly buſineſſes at certaine houres, on which euen in your houſes reade ouer the word of God, and dedicate your ſelues wholie to his mercie, that they may be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelie fulfilled in you, which is written concerning the happie man. For, <hi>in the law of the Lord will he meditate day &amp; night:</hi> And that, <hi>Bleſſed are they that ſearch his teſtimonies, and ſeeke him with their whole heart:</hi> And that, <hi>Thy words haue I hid within my whole heart, that I might not ſinne agaynſt thee.</hi> For as you haue heard, as he which hideth Gods words in his heart ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not: ſo alſo he which hideth them not ceaſeth not to ſinne. For, if it ſufficeth not buyers and ſellers, to make their gaines of one ſort of ware only, but they get many wares by which they may encreaſe their ſubſtance: and if Huſbandmen do their endeuour to ſowe diuers kinds of ſeedes, whereby they may ſufficiently prouide meate for
<pb facs="tcp:6636:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> them and theirs; how much rather in ſpirituall gaines ought it not to ſuffice you, that you heare the diuine leſſons in the Church, but in your hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and at your meales: and when the daies be ſhort, ſome houres in the nights alſo ye ought to labour earneſtly in diuine reading, to the end, that ye may get you ſpirituall wheate into the Barne of your heart, and in the treaſuries of your ſoules lay vp the <hi>Pearles</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> that when at the day of iudgement yee ſhall come before the iudgement ſeate of the eternall Iudge, ye may bee found, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Clothed, and not naked. <hi>Auguſt. ad frat. in Erem. Serm. 56.</hi>
               </hi> If through ignorance, or otherwiſe by ſinning yee haue done any thing againſt God, be not ſlacke through your well doings to amend it, carefully calling this to your remembrance, that the maried man liue in his houſe quietly and peaceably as it becommeth a good Chriſtian, that he honour his father and mother, that he loue his wife, that with very great diſcipline he teach his Children the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith and law of God, to the end, that they may knowe how to loue, feare, and honour God. For this thing is acceptable before God. <hi>Auguſt. ad frat. in Erem. Serm. 64. <hi>Hearken, all ye of the world, that haue Wiues and Children, how S.</hi> Paule <hi>the Apoſtle of Chriſt, commandeth you to reade the Scriptures, and that not ſleightly, or as by the waye, but with great diligence.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6636:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> Chryſost. in Epiſt. ad Coll. Hom. 9.</hi> Hearken not hereto only here in the Church, but alſo at home; let the huſband with the wife, let the father with the childe, talke together of theſe matters, and both to and fro, let them both enquire, and giue their iudgements: and would God they would begin this good cuſtome. <hi>Idem in Ioh. Hom. 2.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="religious_treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:6636:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Touching the duetie of Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, for the dayly exerciſing of their <hi>families in Chriſt his Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Authoritie of the Scriptures. Gen. 18, 19. Exod. 20, 10. Ioſh. 24, 15. 1. King. 10, 5, 8. Heſt. 4, 16. Pſalm. 101. Iohn. 4, 53. Actes. 10, 2, 16, 15, 31, 32, 33, 34, 18, 8. Rom. 16, 5. 1. Cor. 1, 11, 16, 15. Coll. 4, 15. 1. Tim. 3, 4, 12, 5, 8. 2. Tim. 4, 19. Philem. 2. Iudgement of the Learned.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the good man of the houſe is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of his bed, let him go about none other thing, then that, that hee may be doing and talking of ſuch matters: as by which his whole houſhold may profit more and more in Religion. And as for the good wife of the houſe, let her be verie vigilant, and looke well about her houſe: but let her mutch more care that her whole family di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently ſtudie and do the things that pertaine vnto heauen. For if in our worldly affayres, before we diſpoſe the things that concerne our owne houſes, we firſt of all care for the ſeruices which we owe to the Common-wealth, leaſt for ſuch du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, we be drawne into the Lawe, puniſhed, and with ſhame diſcredited; how much more in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall matters ought we firſt to take order for the
<pb facs="tcp:6636:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> things that belong to God the creatour, and King of all things: leaſt we be perforce haled to the place where is gnaſhing of teeth, <hi>Chriſoſt. in Matth. Hom. 78.</hi> When he ſpeaketh of the Church in <hi>Nymphaes</hi> houſe, we ought to remember, that in one houſhold, there is preſcribed, what manner ones it becommeth all Chriſtian houſholds to be: to wit: that they bee ſo manye little Churches. Wherefore, let euerye one knowe, that this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den is layd vpon him, that he inſtruct his houſe in the feare of the Lord, that he keepe it in holie diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, &amp; to be ſhort, that he there make a repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Church. <hi>Calvin in Col. c. 4, 15.</hi> They were well inſtructed which obeied to be Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed without reſiſtance: which thing declareth, that maiſters in their houſes ought to be as Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to their families, that from the higheſt to the loweſt, they may obey the will of God: <hi>Geneva</hi> note vpon <hi>Gen. 17. verſe 23.</hi> Haſt thou bought thee a Seruant? teach him, and commaund him to do the things that pertaine to the knowledge, ſeruice, and Religion of God, that he may be gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and quiet toward his other fellow-ſeruants, and all other wayes vertuous. Euery mans houſe is a certaine Citie, and euerye man is a Prince ouer his houſe. In ritch mens houſes this thing is plainly to be ſeene, where-as there be both Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors with demeanes, and Stewards, Bayliffs, ouerſeers, and officers one aboue another. But I
<pb facs="tcp:6636:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſay alſo that the houſe euen of poore men is a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; for euen in this there be alſo principalities, for ſo much as that the Huſband beareth rule ouer the Wife, and the Wife ouer the men-ſeruants, and the men-ſeruants are aboue the women: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, Huſbands and Wiues rule theyr Children. Doeſt thou not thinke then the good man of the houſe to be as it were a certaine King, hauing ſo many Princes ſubiect to him, and that it is good reaſon, that of all others he ſhould be moſt ſkilfull to gouerne, and moſt ciuill: <hi>Chryſoſt. in Epheſ. Serm. 22.</hi> Verely I am of that minde, that then there was no family to be found, in which there was not either the Maiſter or Miſtreſſe, either the Sonne, or the Daughter, or at leaſt-wiſe, ſome one or other of the houſehold, that could not at appointed times reade certaine Chapters of the holie Bible, and indifferently well expound all the profitableſt places in them. The holye bookes were at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time coumpted for moſt precious houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold-ſtuffe: and euery houſe was after a ſort (I ſay) not only a Schoole, but euen a Church alſo adorned and beawtified with the daily exerciſes of reading the Scriptures, interpretations, and prayers. <hi>Hyp. lib. 1. De quotid. ſac. Script. lect.</hi> ſpeaking of the dayes in S. <hi>Hieroms</hi> time, when he wrote to <hi>Sunia</hi> and <hi>Fretela.</hi> There is no houſe that can rightly be called a Chriſtian houſe, except the word of Chriſt dwell in it, and ſome-thing be
<pb facs="tcp:6636:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> dayly vttered and heard, as touching holie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or points of Diuinitie. Euery well ordered, and true Chriſtian family, ought to repreſent the forme and ſimilitude, as well of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale as alſo in ſpeciall of the Church, and that moſt chiefely by the continuall handling and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting of the word of God, <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi> Doeſt thou then thinke that thoſe houſholds are diſordered, and not rightly ruled, where there is no dayly meditation of Religion kept?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi> Such families may rather be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a ſincke of ſinne, where the people are carefull of worldly proffits, and vaine delight, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of the word of God, and true Religion. And therefore they are in this caſe often-times nearer to deſtruction: <hi>Mayſter Shut in the teſtimonie of a true faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi> What doeſt thou thinke of thoſe Mayſters, which do not teach their Seruaunts the true knowledge of God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi> How-ſo-euer they take them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, it is manifeſt, that they haue not ſo mutch as the ſhewe of Chriſtianitie, nor of anye godly minde: for can thoſe be good, which ſuffer theyr family (which ſhould be a little Church) to be ſo ful of wickedneſſe, as roiſting, ſwearing, rayling, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, quarelling, and all other filthineſſe (that is
<pb facs="tcp:6636:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> euen a little Hell) and neuer goe about to examine and inſtruct them in anye goodneſſe: So that they haue their worke done well in the weeke day, they care not where they become vpon the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day, they neuer examine them how they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by the word, <hi>Mayſter Gyff. in his Catechiſme.</hi> The third commaundement is broken, by omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and neglecting the occaſions and oportunitie that is giuen to enſtruct other, and to bring them to the acknowledging of the truth, eſpecially chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and others that are committed to our truſt and charge, <hi>Vrſinus in his Catechiſme.</hi> The houſholder tranſgreſſeth the fourth Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who eſpecially on the Saboths and feſtiuall dayes, ſo alſo ſome-time on the worke dayes hath not propounded, or cauſed to be propounded and taught to his Children and family, the chiefe heads of Chriſtian Religion, namely, ſuch as be taught and contayned in the Catechiſme. <hi>Hyp. in the triall of a mans owne ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maiſters and Dames are required in the ſixth Commaundement, to enſtruct their ſeruants in Religion, to ſee that they beſtowe not the Saboth day, nor any ſuch other time lawfully exempted in worldly affayres, but in diuine ſeruice, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther works, as becommeth ſuch oportunities. And the ſayd Maiſters and Dames do breake the ſixt Commaundement, when they do not diligently
<pb facs="tcp:6636:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> traine vp their ſeruants in Religion and vertue, when they ſet their ſeruaunts about their owne bellies, or other worldly affaires vpon the Saboth day, eſpeciallye then, or at any time elſe, when of right they ſhould be at Seruice or Sermons: <hi>Ma. Bunny in a ſhort ſumme of Chriſtian Religion, vnder the conſideration of the ten Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Counſell of <hi>Nice</hi> decreed, that no Chriſtian man ſhould be without the Bible in his houſe, <hi>Corn. Agrip. de vanit. ſcient. c. 100.</hi> Take the Bible into your hands in your houſes at home. At home in our houſes let vs apply the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the holye Scriptures, <hi>Chriſoſt. in Gen. Hom. 28.</hi> Thinke it not ſufficient, that ye heare the Scriptures in the Church onelye: but alſo in your houſes at home, either reade your ſelues, or, get ſome other to reade vnto you, and heare them willingly, <hi>Auguſt. de temp. Ser. 55.</hi> Let the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Gods word begin to take vp and vſe the time, that furious Table-playing is wont to take from vs. In ſtead of idle Tables, biting ieſts, and venemous detractions, let holie conferences, and communications of the Scriptures come in place, <hi>Auguſt. de temp. Serm. 56. Augustine <hi>to Volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi>
               </hi> and in certayne of his Sermons, craueth of the people, whoſe Paſtor he was, that in ſtead of Dice, Cards, and other paſtimes, they would
<pb facs="tcp:6636:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> get them, and reade the holy Scriptures, <hi>Bulling. Comp. Chriſt. Relig. lib. 1. c. 7.</hi> Let one of you take in hand the holy Boke, and let him call his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours about him, and by the heauenly words, let him water, and refreſh both their minds, and alſo his owne, <hi>Chryſoſt. in Gen. Hom. 6.</hi> Heare the holy Scriptures both in the Church as ye haue beene accuſtomed, and alſo in your houſes, reade them ouer againe. If any be ſo buſied, that before meate hee cannot ſtudie the holye Scripture, let it not grieue him euen at his ſmall repaſt, to peruſe ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the holy Scriptures, that as his fleſh is fed with meate, ſo his Soule may be refreſhed with Gods word: that the whole man, that is to ſay, both the outward and the inward may riſe fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with an holy and wholeſome banquet. For if the fleſh only be refreſhed, and the Soule not fed with Gods word, the mayde is filled, and the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe grieued with hunger. And howe vniuſt a thing this is, your holyneſſe cannot bee ignorant. And therefore as I haue alreadie ſayd, ye ought to reade and heare the diuine Scriptures with ſuch deſire, as that both in your houſes, and elſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer yee ſhall be, yee maye be able both to frame your ſpeach of them, and alſo to teach others the ſame, that in minde as in a cleane Soule alwayes calling to remembrance the word of God, ye may be able both to receiue for your ſelues the profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:6636:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> iuyce, that is, the ſpirituall ſence, and alſo by the helpe of God, yee may bee able to bring and ſhewe the ſame to others; that, that may be fulfilled in you which is written, <hi>and thy cup that runneth ouer, is very excellent, <hi>Auguſt. De temp. Serm. 56.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:6636:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Concluſion to each well diſpoſed <hi>Chriſtian, conteyning the vſe</hi> of this Table.</head>
            <p>MAruaile not I pray thee good Chriſtian, that I haue not expreſſed the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſacred Scriptures word for word, but onely noted them by booke, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and verſe: I hope that eyther thou haſte a Bible of thine owne, or elſe by extreame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie wanting it, yet according to thy chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an bounden dutie thou either art, or hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth wilt be a diligent frequenter of the place, where thou mayſt haue the vſe of it. The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by whome, the times at which, and the places where-in the priuate exerciſe of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould be begon and continued, this moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion playnely ſheweth. For matter what ſhould in this exerciſe be handled, and manner how the ſame with profit may be done, together with the aunſwering of ſuch obiections as may be made againſt it, the worthy works heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully gone ouer, whoſe Titles heere thou haſt already, will ſufficiently inſtruct thee. In fine, vpon the reading, or hearing of this monition, for the glorie of Gods Goſpell, the ſafety of thine owne ſoule, and the good enſample of others, in the tender bowels of chriſtian loue, I
<pb facs="tcp:6636:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> beſeech thee accept this councell willingly; ſo many of theſe paſsing good Authors, or their like, as thou ſhalt be able, prouide ſpeedely: ſtudie them thoroughly, commit them to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie carefully, thy knowledge heere-in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to others gladly; frame thy doings accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly: cry to God, to God euen the Father, by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, crye in dayly prayer for theſe and other graces neceſſary to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in moſt plentifull ſort to be powred vpon his Church vniuerſall, our moſt gratious godly Soueraigne, the whole Nobilitie, the whole Miniſterie, all places of learning, and the whole Comminalty of this land: &amp; for the continuall remembrance of theſe things, I praye thee let this booke be in ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient place, where it may bee moſt in ſight, not onlye for thine owne, but alſo for the vſe of all ſuch as do be long, or reſort vnto thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Farewell in the Lord from <hi>Priſton,</hi> in <hi>Sommerſet.</hi>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Thyne, from the verie heart-roote in Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Thomas Wats,</hi> Preacher of Gods Word.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_religious_works">
            <pb facs="tcp:6636:12"/>
            <head>Certaine Titles of zealous mens learned workes, publiſhed for the gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and edification of Gods Saincts, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in our Engliſh tongue, and heere ſet downe by order of their eaſineſſe, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the briefeſt and playneſt, and ſo proceeding to the larger, and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The little Catechiſme with additions.</item>
               <item>Maister Somes Catechiſme.</item>
               <item>The Summe of Christian Religion.</item>
               <item>Maister Derings Catechiſme.</item>
               <item>Maister Nowels little Catechiſme.</item>
               <item>Maister Giffards Catechiſme.</item>
               <item>Maister Woods forme of Catechizing.</item>
               <item>Maister Nowels middle Catechiſme.</item>
               <item>Zacharias <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus Catechiſme.</item>
               <item>Mayster Beacons Catechiſme.</item>
               <item>Mayster Bullingers Decades.</item>
               <item>Wolfgangus Muſculus common places.</item>
               <item>M. Calvins Institutions.</item>
               <item>D. Peter Martirs common places.</item>
               <item>B. Iewels Reply, and</item>
               <item>Defence of the Apologie.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6636:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
